Chapter 81. The Peekquad meets the Virgin.
The predestinated day arrived, and we duly met the ship Yungfra, Derek Dair,
master of Bremen. At one time, the greatest whailing people in the world.
The Dutch and Germans are now among the least. But here and there, at very wide
intervals of latitude and longitude, you still occasionally meet with their flag in the Pacific.
For some reason, the Yungfra seemed quite eager to pay her respects, while
yet some distance from the Peekquad, she rounded too, and dropping a boat, her
captain was impelled toward us, impatiently standing in the boughs instead of the stern.
"What has he in his hand there?" cried Starbucks, pointing to something
wavingly held by the German.
"Impossible. A lamp feeder." "Not that," said Stub. No, no, it's a coffee pot,
Mr. Starbucks. He's coming off to make us our coffee, is the Yarmman. Don't you
see that big tin can there alongside of him? That's his boiling water. Oh, he's
all right, is the Yarmman.
Get along with you, cried Flask. It's a lamp feeder and an oil can. He's out of
oil and has come of begging.
However curious it may seem for an oil ship to be borrowing oil on the whale
ground, and however much it may inadvertently contradict the old proverb
about carrying coals to Newcastle, yet sometimes such a thing really happens,
and in the present case, Captain Derek Dair did indubitably conduct a lamp
feeder, as Flask did declare.
As he mounted the deck, Ahab abruptly accosted him, without at all heeding
what he had in his hand, but in his broken lingo, the German soon evinced
his complete ignorance of the white whale, immediately turning the
conversation to his lamp feeder and oil can, with some remarks touching his
having to turn into his hammock at night in profound darkness, his last drop of
breman oil being gone, and not a single flying fish yet captured to supply the deficiency.
concluding by hinting that his ship was indeed what in the fishery is
technically called a clean one, that is, an empty one, well deserving the name of
Jungfra, or the Virgin, his necessities supplied Derek departed,
but he had not gained his ship's side when whales were almost simultaneously
raised from the mast heads of both vessels, and so eager for the chase was
Derek, that without pausing to put his oil can lamp feeder aboard. He slewed
round his boat and made after the Leviathan lamp feeders.
Now the game having risen to the lure, he and the other three German boats that
soon followed him had considerably the start of the Peekquad's keels. There
were eight whales, an average pod. Aware of their danger, they were going all a
breast with great speed straight before the wind, rubbing their flanks as
closely as so many spans of horses in harness, they left a great wide wake, as
though continually unrolling a great wide parchment upon the sea.
Full in this rapid wake and many fathoms in the rear, swam a huge humped old
bull, which by his comparatively slow progress, as well as by the unusual
yellowish incrustations overgrowing him, seemed afflicted with the jaundice, or
some other infirmity. Whether this whale belonged to the pod in advance seemed
questionable, for it is not customary for such venerable Leviathans to be at
all social. Nevertheless, he stuck to their wake, though indeed their backwater must have him,
because the white bone or swell at his broad muzzle was a dashed one, like the
swell formed when two hostile currents meet. His spout was short, slow, and
laborious, coming forth with a choking sort of gush, and spending itself in
torn shreds, followed by strange subterranean commotions in him, which
seemed to have eress at his other buried extremity, causing the waters behind him to upbubble.
"Who's got some paragoric?" said Stub.
He has the stomach ache, I'm afraid.
Lord, think of having half an acre of stomach ache. Adverse winds are holding
mad Christmas in him, boys. It's the first foul wind I ever knew to blow from
a stern. But look, did ever whale yaw so before? It must be he's lost his tiller.
As an overladen indium bearing down the Hindustan coast with a deckload of
frightened horses, caren, buries, rolls, and wallows on her way. So did this old
whale heave his aged bulk. and now and then, partly turning over on his cumbous
ribs, exposed the cause of his devious wake in the unnatural stump of his
starboard fin. Whether he had lost that fin in battle or had been born without
it, it were hard to say. "Only wait a bit, old chap, and I'll give you a sling
for that wounded arm!" cried Cruel Flask, pointing to the whale line near
him. "Mind he don't sling thee with it!"
cried Starbucks. Give way or the German will have him. With one intent, all the
combined rival boats were pointed for this one fish, because not only was he
the largest, and therefore the most valuable whale, but he was nearest to
them, and the other whales were going with such great velocity, moreover, as
almost to defy pursuit for the time. At this juncture, the Peekquad's Keels had
shot by the three German boats last lowered, but from the great start he had
had, Derek's boat still led the chase, though every moment neared by his
foreign rivals. The only thing they feared was that from being already so
nigh to his mark, he would be unable to dart his iron before they could
completely overtake and pass him. As for Derek, he seemed quite confident that
this would be the case, and occasionally, with a deriding gesture,
shook his lamp feeder at the other boats. "The ungracious and ungrateful
dog!" cried Starbucks. "He mocks and dares me with the very poor box I filled
for him not 5 minutes ago." Then, in his old intense whisper, "Give way,
greyhounds! Dog to it!" "I tell you what it is, men!" cried Stub to his crew.
It's against my religion to get mad, but I'd like to eat that villainous yarm.
Pull, won't you? Are you going to let that rascal beat you? Do you love
brandy? A hog's head of brandy then to the best man. Come, why don't some of
you burst a blood vessel? Who's that been dropping an anchor overboard? We
don't budge an inch. We're be calmed.
Hello. Here's grass growing in the boat's bottom. And by the lord, the mass
there budding. This won't do, boys. Look at that yarm. The short and long of it
is, men. Will you spit fire or not? Oh, see the suds he makes, cried flask,
dancing up and down. What a hump. Oh, do pile on the beef. Lays like a log. Oh,
my lads do spring. Slapjacks and quay hogs for supper. You know my lads. Baked
clams and muffins. Oh, do do spring.
He's a 100 barreler. Don't lose him now.
Oh, don't don't see that yarm. Oh, won't you pull for your duff, my lads? Such a
sogg. Such a sggger. Don't you love sperm? There goes $3,000, men. A bank. A
whole bank. The bank of England. Oh, do do.
What's that yarm about now?
At this moment, Derek was in the act of pitching his lamp feeder at the
advancing boats and also his oil can, perhaps with the double view of
retarding his rivals way, and at the same time economically accelerating his
own by the momentary impetus of the backward toss. The unmannerly Dutch
Dogger, cried Stub. Pull now, men, like 50,000 line of battleship loads of
red-haired devils. What do you say, Tashego? Are you the man to snap your
spine in two and 20 pieces for the honor
of old gay head? What do you say? I say pull like godamn, cried the Indian.
Fiercely but evenly incited by the taunts of the German, the Peekquad's
three boats now began ranging almost depressed, and so disposed momentarily
neared him. In that fine, loose chioalous attitude of the headsman, when
drawing near to his prey, the three mates stood up proudly, occasionally
backing the after orsman with an exhilarating cry of, "There she slides
now. Harrah, for the white ash breeze, down with the yarm, sail over him." But
so decided an original start had Derek had that spite of all their gallantry,
he would have proved the victor in this race, had not a righteous judgment
descended upon him in a crab which caught the blade of his midship orsman.
While this clumsy lover was striving to free his white ash, and while in
consequence Derek's boat was nigh to capsizing, and he thundering away at his
men in a mighty rage, that was a good time for Starbuck, Stub, and Flast. With
a shout they took a mortal start forward, and slantingly ranged up on the
Germans quarter. An instant more, and all four boats were diagonally in the
whale's immediate wake, while stretching from them on both sides was the foaming
swell that he made.
It was a terrific, most pitiable and maddening sight. The whale was now going
head out, and sending his spout before him in a continual tormented jet, while
his one poor fin beat his side in an agony of fright. "Now to this hand! Now
to that!" He yawed in his faltering flight, and still at every billow that
he broke, he spasmotically sank in the sea, or sideways rolled towards the sky,
his one beating fin. So have I seen a bird with clipped wing making a frighted
broken circles in the air, vainly striving to escape the paradical hawks.
But the bird has a voice, and with plaintiff cries, will make known her
fear. But the fear of this vast dumb brood of the sea was chained up and
enchanted in him. He had no voice save that choking respiration through his
spiracle, and this made the sight of him unspeakably pitiable, while still in his
amazing bulk, port cullous jaw, and omnipotent tail, there was enough to
appall the stoutest man who so pied, seeing now that but a very few moments
more would give the Peekquad's boats the advantage, and rather than be thus
foiled of his game, Derek chose to hazard what to him must have seemed a
most unusually long dart heir the last chance would forever escape. But no
sooner did his harpooner stand up for the stroke than all three tigers, Queig,
Tashego, and Dagu instinctively sprang to their feet, and standing in a
diagonal row simultaneously pointed their barbs and darted over the head of
the German harpooner there three Nantucket irons entered the whale.
blinding vapors of foam and white fire.
The three boats, in the first fury of the whales head-long rush, bumped the
Germans aside with such force that both Derek and his baffled harpooner were
spilled out and sailed over by the three flying keels. "Don't be afraid, my
butter boxes!" cried Stub, casting a passing glance upon them as he shot by.
"You'll be picked up presently." "All right, I saw some sharks of Stern St.
Bernard's dogs, you know, relieve distressed travelers. Hurrah! This is
the way to sail now. Every keel a sunbeam. Hurrah! Here we go. Like three
tin kettles at the tail of a mad cougar.
This puts me in mind of fastening to an elephant in a tillbury on a plane. Makes
the wheel spokes fly, boys, when you fasten to him that way. And there's
danger of being pitched out, too, when you strike a hill. Hurrah! This is the
way a fellow feels when he's going to Davy Jones. All a rush down an endless
inclined plane. Harrah, this whale carries the everlasting mail.
But the monster's run was a brief one, giving a sudden gasp, he tumultuously
sounded. With a grading rush, the three lines flew around the loggerheads with
such force as to gouge deep grooves in them. While so fearful were the
harpooners that this rapid sounding would soon exhaust the lines, that using
all their dextrous might, they caught repeated smoking turns with the rope to
hold on, till at last, owing to the perpendicular strain from the leadlined
chocks of the boats, whence the three ropes went straight down into the blue,
the gunnels of the boughs were almost even with the water, while the three
sterns were tilted high in the air, and the whale soon ceasing to sound for some
time they remained in that attitude, fearful of expending more line, though
the position was a little ticklish. But though boats have been taken down and
lost in this way, yet it is this holding on, as it is called, this hooking up by
the sharp barbs of his live flesh from the back. This it is that often torments
the Leviathan into soon rising again to meet the sharp lance of his foes. Yet
not to speak of the peril of the thing, it is to be doubted whether this course
is always the best, for it is but reasonable to presume that the longer
the stricken whale stays underwater, the more he is exhausted, because owing to
the enormous surface of him, in a full-grown sperm whale, something less
than 2,000 square ft, the pressure of the water is immense. We all know what
an astonishing atmospheric weight we ourselves stand up under, even here
above ground in the air. How vast then the burden of a whale bearing on his
back a column of 200 fathoms of ocean.
It must at least equal the weight of 50 atmospheres. One whaleman has estimated
it at the weight of 20 line of battleships with all their guns and
stores and men on board.
As the three boats lay there on that gently rolling sea, gazing down into its
eternal blue noon, and as not a single groan or cry of any sort, nay, not so
much as a ripple or a bubble, came up from its depths, what landsman would
have thought that beneath all that silence and placidity, the utmost
monster of the seas was writhing and wrenching in agony. Not 8 in of
perpendicular rope were visible at the boughs. Seems it credible that by three
such thin threads the great Leviathan was suspended like the big weight to an
8-day clock. Suspended and to what? To three bits of board. Is this the
creature of whom it was once so triumphantly said, "Tou fill his skin
with barbed irons, or his head with fish spears? The sword of him that layeth at
him cannot hold. The spear the dart nor the habon. He esteemth iron as straw.
The arrow cannot make him flee. Darts are counted as stubble. He laughth at
the shaking of a spear. This the creature, this he, oh that unfulfillment
should follow the prophets. For with the strength of a thousand thighs in his
tail, Leviathan had run his head under the mountains of the sea to hide him
from the Peekquad's fish spears.
In that sloping afternoon sunlight, the shadows that the three boats sent down
beneath the surface must have been long enough and broad enough to shade half
Xerxes army. Who can tell how appalling to the wounded whale must have been such
huge phantoms flitting over his head?
"Stand by, men! He stirs!" cried Starbucks, as the three lines suddenly
vibrated in the water, distinctly conducting upwards to them, as by
magnetic wires, the life and death throbs of the whale, so that every orman
felt them in his seat. The next moment, relieved in great part from the downward
strain at the boughs, the boats gave a sudden bounce upward, as a small ice
field will when a dense herd of white bears are scared from it into the sea.
Haul in. Paul in," cried Starbuck again.
"He's rising." The lines of which hardly an instant before, not one hand's
breath, could have been gained, were now in long, quick coils flung back, all
dripping into the boats, and soon the whale broke water within two ships lengths of the hunters.
His motions plainly denoted his extreme exhaustion. In most land animals, there
are certain valves or floodgates in many of their veins, whereby when wounded,
the blood is, in some degree at least, instantly shut off in certain
directions. Not so with the whale, one of whose peculiarities it is to have an
entire nonvalular structure of the blood vessels, so that when pierced, even by
so small a point as a harpoon, a deadly drain is at once begun upon his whole
arterial system. And when this is heightened by the extraordinary pressure
of water at a great distance below the surface, his life may be said to pour
from him in incessant streams. Yet so vast is the quantity of blood in him,
and so distant and numerous its interior fountains, that he will keep thus
bleeding and bleeding for a considerable period, even as in a drought a river
will flow, whose source is in the wellsp springs of far off and undicernable
hills. Even now, when the boats pulled upon the whale, and perilously drew over
his swaying flukes, and the lances were darted into him, they were followed by
steady jets from the new maid wound, which kept continually playing, while
the natural spout hole in his head was only at intervals, however rapid,
sending its afrighted moisture into the air. From this last vent, no blood yet
came, because no vital part of him had thus far been struck. His life, as they
significantly call it, was untouched.
As the boats now more closely surrounded him, the whole upper part of his form,
with much of it that is ordinarily submerged, was plainly revealed. His
eyes, or rather the places where his eyes had been, were beheld. As strange
misgrown masses gather in the kn holes of the noblest oaks when prostrate, so
from the points which the whale's eyes had once occupied now protruded blind
bulbs, horribly pitiable to see. But pity there was none. for all his old age
and his one arm and his blind eyes. He must die the death and be murdered in
order to light the gay bridles and other merry makings of men, and also to
illuminate these solemn churches that preach unconditional inoffensiveness by
all to all. still rolling in his blood, at last he partially disclosed a
strangely discolored bunch or protrance the size of a bushel low down on the
flank. A nice spot, cried Flask. Just let me prick him there once. A vast,
cried Starbucks. There's no need of that. But humane Starbucks was too late.
At the instant of the dart, an ulcerous jet shot from this cruel wound, and
goated by it into more than sufferable anguish, the whale, now spouting thick
blood with swift fury, blindly darted at the craft, be spattering them and their
gloring crews all over with showers of gore, capsizing Flask's boat, and
marring the boughs. It was his death stroke, for by this time so spent was he
by loss of blood that he helplessly rolled away from the wreck he had made,
lay panting on his side, impotently flapped with his stumped fin, then over
and over slowly revolved like a waning world, turned up the white secrets of
his belly, lay like a log, and died. It was most pitious that last expiring
spout, as when by unseen hands the water is gradually drawn off from some mighty
fountain, and with half stifled melancholy gurglings, the spray column
lowers and lowers to the ground, so the last long dying spout of the whale.
Soon, while the crews were awaiting the arrival of the ship, the body showed
symptoms of sinking with all its treasures unrivaled. Immediately by
Starbucks orders, lines were secured to it at different points, so that airong
every boat was a boy, the sunken whale being suspended a few inches beneath
them by the cords. By very heedful management, when the ship drew nigh, the
whale was transferred to her side, and was strongly secured there by the
stiffest fluke chains, for it was plain that unless artificially upheld, the
body would at once sink to the bottom.
It's so chance that almost upon first cutting into him with the spade, the
entire length of a corroded harpoon was found embedded in his flesh on the lower
part of the bunch before described. But as the stumps of harpoons are frequently
found in the dead bodies of captured whales, with the flesh perfectly healed
around them, and no prominence of any kind to denote their place, therefore
there must needs have been some other unknown reason in the present case fully
to account for the ulceration alluded to. But still more curious was the fact
of a lance head of stone being found in him, not far from the buried iron, the
flesh perfectly firm about it. Who had darted that stone lance, and when it
might have been darted by some Norwest Indian long before America was discovered?
What other marvels might have been rummaged out of this monstrous cabinet,
there is no telling, but a sudden stop was put to further discoveries by the
ships being unprecedentedly dragged over sideways to the sea, owing to the body's
immensely increasing tendency to sink.
However, Starbucks, who had the ordering of affairs, hung on to it to the last,
hung on to it so resolutely indeed, that when at length the ship would have been
capsized, if still persisting in locking arms with the body, then when the
command was given to break clear from it, such was the immovable strain upon
the timber heads to which the fluke chains and cables were fastened, that it
was impossible to cast them off.
Meantime, everything in the pequad was a slant. To cross to the other side of the
deck was like walking up the steep gabled roof of a house. The ship groaned
and gasped. Many of the ivory inlays of her bull works and cabins were started
from their places by the unnatural dislocation. In vain hand spikes and
crows were brought to bear upon the immovable fluke chains to pry them a
drift from the timberheads, and so low had the whale now settled that the
submerged ends could not be at all approached, while every moment whole
tons of ponderosity seemed added to the sinking bulk, and the ship seemed on the
point of going over. "Hold on, hold on, won't you?" cried Stub to the body.
"Don't be in such a devil of a hurry to sink." By thundermen, we must do
something or go for it. No use prying there. I've asked, I say, with your
handspikes, and run one of you for a prayer book and a pen knife, and cut the
big chains. Knife? I I cried Qui Quag, and seizing the carpenter's heavy
hatchet, he leaned out of a port hole and steel to iron, began slashing at the
largest fluke chains. But a few strokes full of sparks were given when the
exceeding strain affected the rest. With a terrific snap, every fastening went a
drift. The ship writed, the carcass sank.
Now, this occasional inevitable sinking of the recently killed sperm whale is a
very curious thing, nor has any fisherman yet adequately accounted for
it. Usually, the dead sperm whale floats with great buoyancy, with its side or
belly considerably elevated above the surface. If the only whales that thus
sank were old, meager, and brokenhearted creatures, their pads of lard
diminished, and all their bones heavy and rumatic, then you might with some
reason assert that this sinking is caused by an uncommon specific gravity
in the fish so sinking, consequent upon this absence of buoyant matter in him.
But it is not so, for young whales in the highest health and swelling with
noble aspirations, prematurely cut off in the warm flush and may of life, with
all their panting lard about them, even these brrawy, buoyant heroes do sometimes sink.
Be it said, however, that the sperm whale is far less liable to this
accident than any other species. Where one of that sort go down, 20 right
whales do. This difference in the species is no doubt imputable in no
small degree to the greater quantity of bone in the right whale, his Venetian
blinds alone, sometimes weighing more than a ton. From this incumbrance the
sperm whale is wholly free. But there are instances where after the lapse of
many hours or several days, the sunken whale again rises, more buoyant than in
life. But the reasons of this are obvious. Gases are generated in him. He
swells to a prodigious magnitude, becomes a sort of animal balloon. A line
of battleship could hardly keep him under. Then in the shore whailing on
soundings among the bays of New Zealand, when a right whale gives token of
sinking, they fasten boys to him with plenty of rope, so that when the body
has gone down, they know where to look for it when it shall have ascended again.
It was not long after the sinking of the body that a cry was heard from the
Peekquad's mast heads, announcing that the Yungfra was again lowering her
boats, though the only spout in sight was that of a finback belonging to the
species of uncapturable whales because of its incredible power of swimming.
Nevertheless, the finback spout is so similar to the sperm whales that by
unskillful fishermen, it is often mistaken for it, and consequently Derek
and all his host were now in valiant chase of this unnerable brute. The
virgin crowding all sail made after her four young keels, and thus they all
disappeared, far to lure, still in bold, hopeful chase.
Oh, many are the finbacks and many are the Dereks, my friend.